Learn how to use Nest.js to build
scalable back-end applications. In this
course, you'll explore controllers,
services, modules, decorators, pipes,
guards, and exception handling, all
while building the profile feature for
Dev Match, a dating app for developers.
You'll learn all about Nex.js's modular
architecture, TypeScript support, and
built-in tools to create clean, testable
code. Don, the developer from Scribba,
developed this course.
Welcome to Scribba's intro to NestJS
course. If you're looking to level up
your backend skills, move beyond just
building basic express apps, and
challenge yourself with a more robust
and scalable framework, this course is
for you. Let me go ahead and give you a
quick overview of what Nest is about and
some of the reasons you might want to
consider building with it.
Nest uses classes, decorators, and
TypeScript to help create clean testable
code and provides first class dependency
injection out of the box through its
dependency injection system. One thing
to note though is you can actually make
Nest work with JavaScript 2 if you're
not too familiar with TypeScript just
yet. Nest has similar module and
dependency injection patterns to Angular
and Java Spring Boot. So, if you're
familiar with that, you'll feel right at
home with working with Nest. If you
aren't familiar with either, don't
worry. This course is meant to be
beginner friendly and you will become
more comfortable with it. Anyways, if
you've built APIs with Express, that's
great. Nest actually uses Express under
the hood, so it's compatible with a lot
of Express middleware. Or if you prefer
Fastify, that's an option in Nest as
well. One thing that people love about
Nest is its opinionated architecture. It
organizes features into modules and uses
the dependency injection system to solve
common dependency management problems
you get with node apps just using
express. It does a great job at keeping
things modular and Nesta is great at
building both monoliths and
microservices.
In terms of market demand, although it's
scalable for large applications and that
is a strength of it, it's actually
mainly used in small to medium-siz
companies. So a lot of people think that
it's meant for just enterprise apps and
that's not the case. The usage of it is
just increasing over time and it's
actually become one of the most popular
frameworks in the node ecosystem. Here
are a few companies that have built apps
with Nest. This obviously isn't a full
list, but I want to level with you. I
know a lot of you are probably taking
this course to level up as a back-end
dev and the node ecosystem and just
increase your marketability. We need to
have an honest conversation.
Most aspiring developers are just
building basic express apps. A lot of
people are just going through the same
MS stack tutorial and then you're also
competing with other people that are
going through the same MS stack
tutorials. A lot of backend positions in
web development, especially with the
larger applications, use heavier
frameworks. Nest has a lot of depth to
it. Being able to demonstrate that
you're familiar with and can build
things with a more scalable framework
like Nest looks way better than piecing
together a simple Express app. If you
want to stand out more, you need to do
more. Building things with Nest will
force you to set a higher bar for
yourself and give you confidence in
building more professional applications.
Now, the Nest CLI, which we'll use
later, is really convenient and speeds
up the scaffolding when creating new
features, and you can trust that it
starts you off with the best Nest
conventions. Honestly, after I switched
over to Nest, I gained a renewed
excitement and working in the Node
ecosystem, and I'm really excited to
teach you how to build things with it.
So, let's get started.
In this course, we're building Dev
Match, a simple dating app for
developers. Now, this is meant to be
beginner friendly. So, we'll just be
focused on building out the profile
feature for our dating app. But this
feature alone will allow us to get you
much more comfortable with the
fundamentals and be able to start
building something of your own with
Nest. To start working with Nest, you
should at least be familiar with
JavaScript, preferably TypeScript. If
you're not really familiar with
TypeScript, that's okay. We won't be
diving that deep into TypeScript, and
you'll still be able to learn how to use
Nest. You should also be familiar with
Node. Believe it or not, discovering how
abstractions work underneath instead of
jumping into just relying on it is a
fantastic way to learn them. And before
you jump into building something with
Nest, you should have familiarity with
building personal projects with Express.
Think of this as the next step after you
build a few basic Express apps and
you're familiar with routing. While
Scribba has a ton of JavaScript courses
to get you more familiar with it, I
included specific links to the others to
get you up to speed if you haven't
explored the murky waters of the back
end yet. For the TypeScript course,
going through TypeScript fundamentals
and practicing what you learned there
should be sufficient. At the time of
this recording, you'll need at least
version 20 of Node to run Nest. All
right, now that we got all of that out
of the way, let's finally get started.
I'll see you in the next lesson.
Let's go ahead and set up the initial
scaffolding. Especially if this is your
first time with Nest, I highly recommend
you use Nest CLI for this. Let's install
the CLI and packages we'll need to get
up and running. Also, I just want to
give you a heads up. If you're running
this locally, I highly recommend you
follow the steps in Nest documentation.
When it comes to the CLI, we're going to
tweak our commands so that it plays
nicely within Scrambas environment. But
you can actually just use the commands
we use in this course when working on
your project locally if you want. I just
want to give you a heads up as it'll be
slightly different than what you may see
in the documentation. Let's go ahead and
set up the CLI.
So what this command is going to do is
it's going to temporarily install the
CLI. We're going to create a new project
called dev match. We're going to set the
package manager as mpm. We're going to
skip the git setup and install
everything in the current directory. Let
me go ahead and speed through this for
us. All right, Nest is almost set up. We
just need to install our packages.
Perfect. Let's try booting up our
project.
If you're setting this up locally,
normally you'd be able to just go to
localhost 3000 in the browser and see
hello world. With the way Scrimpa
currently records the browser output, we
would need to tweak this slightly to get
it so that the output is properly
captured and shown to you. Rather than
doing that, since this is a backend
course after all, I'd rather use
Scribba's network tool to be able to
simulate a get request. If you've ever
used Postman, it's similar to that. If
you haven't, I highly recommend you try
Postman out for yourself. It's been an
invaluable tool I've used as I built out
APIs. Let's try it out.
Success. As you can see, we're getting a
status code of 200. Let's check the
response. And we see hello world. We've
officially spun up our first Nest app.
It's that easy to get up and running
locally to start building out features.
Now it's time to start getting you more
comfortable with how Nest works. I'll
see you in the next lesson.
Let's go ahead and create our first
module. Modules are great for organizing
components. They help organize code
that's relevant to a specific feature,
helping to maintain clear boundaries and
better organization.
You could use the CLI to generate all of
the boiler plate for a feature like so.
But as we're learning, let's use the CLI
more selectively to generate what we
need as we go through the lessons. Let's
generate our first module.
So what the CLI just did is it created
our profiles feature in the SRC folder.
As we can see, we have a new profiles
folder. We check it out. We have our
module file and then the CLI
conveniently also added the profiles
module to the imports as well. Let's go
ahead and check out our profiles module
file. As you can see, it's pretty empty.
We haven't really added anything yet.
Let's start populating our feature. The
next step is to create our controller
file. Our controller will contain all of
our routes for the profile feature. We
can actually go ahead and use the CLI to
create our controller file as well. CLI
is really convenient.
So, as you can see, it autopop populated
the profiles module. We can now see that
our controller is being imported
properly. Let's go ahead and open up our
controller file. Now, our controller is
empty by default. And what we're going
to do is we're going to start populating
this manually. and we'll get you some
practice with this. One thing you'll
notice is that it also autogenerated a
spec file where we're going to put our
test for our controller in. Now, we're
not going to be writing test in this
course, but I just wanted to make you
aware that this is also generated, but
there's an interesting little symbol
here. This is called a decorator.
They're basically higher order
functions. If you've never heard of a
higher order function before, let's say
you have a function say hello. A
decorator function will take the say
hello function and do some extra stuff
like printing a line before and after
the main function runs. It just adds
additional behavior to the function.
Decorators aren't currently implemented
in JavaScript, but they've been in
Typescript for a while and are enabled
by setting the experimental decorators
compile option in your TS config file
and have evolved over time. Nest sets
this up automatically, so you don't need
to worry about this, though. The main
thing you need to know is that this is
what using a decorator looks like, and
Nest has a ton of built-in decorators
that make your life easier. We'll be
using some of them in this course and
you'll start to get the hang of using
them by the end of it. So, if they look
intimidating, don't worry about it. You
will get more comfortable with them. In
the next lesson, we're going to finally
set up our routes. I'll see you there.
Finally, it's time to start building out
our routes. Now, you'll notice that I
copied and pasted this in. These are the
routes that we're going to be building
out in this course. Let's start with
setting up the route to return all
dating profiles. So, let's go ahead and
import our get decorator.
And with our get decorator, we're going
to call that on a function we're just
going to call find all.
And we're going to go ahead and return
an empty array. So, we're just returning
an empty array to just test if this is
working. Now, before we do that, let me
go ahead and open this up. So, you'll
see in the runner that everything looks
good. What I want to do is break this to
just show you what happens when we break
it. So, let's go ahead and save it here.
You'll notice that we do get an error in
the runner. So, if you ever are
experiencing issues or your app isn't
doing what you think it's doing, the
runner is a really good first choice to
check just to see if something has gone
wrong. So, let's go back to here and fix
it and test it out. And it looks like
everything is rerendered properly. Now,
let's see if our get request actually
works. Let's go to the network tab, and
we can just make a get request to our
profiles endpoint. And it works. So,
we're getting an empty array and a 200
status code back. Success. Now, we might
want to change the status code in the
future, and Nest provides a way to
easily do that. But for now, we're
getting everything back that we need to,
and we have a working get route. So
right now we're returning an empty
array. We'll be returning data once we
get to the service file where you'll
usually hold most of your business logic
in your app. Think of the controller
layer as deciding what to do based on
the request your API receives, what
functions to call, and allowing your
service layer to decide how to do it. If
this doesn't make sense right now,
that's okay. We're going to practice.
For now, let's just focus on getting
more comfortable with setting up routes
and extracting data from the request
object. Now, I think you're ready for
your first challenge. So, let me go
ahead and reset this. I want you to
recreate our get route and just return
an empty array. When you're done with
the challenge, go ahead and submit it
and then we'll go over it together
afterwards. Good luck.
[sighs]
I hope that went well. So, let's go
ahead and restore our get route.
So, we're going to call get
and then create our find all function.
And that's just going to return an empty
array. Let's go ahead and test it in the
network tab.
And success. So, get routes can often
receive query parameters. So, let's just
go ahead and grab a query parameter to
show you other things Nest can do. So,
we import that here. And then we're
going to go ahead and pass in query. And
let's go ahead and grab age. Age is
going to be a number. And then just to
make sure that we're reading this
correctly, we'll go ahead and just pass
in a single profile with age back to the
client. Now let's test it out.
Say age 25. And success. We're getting
back a 200 with an array, a single
profile, and an age of 25. So we are
going to get a lot of practice in this
course. So let me go ahead and reset
this for you and prepare you for your
new challenge. For this challenge, I
want our get route to expect to receive
a query parameter of location and just
return an array with a single object
with the location passed in just like we
did before. All right, good luck.
I hope that went well. So let's go ahead
and import query
and then we're going to call query here
and we want to grab location
and then location is actually going to
be a string. Now let's pass a profile
with location back to the client and
just make sure that we are properly
receiving the query parameter and
passing it through. Now, let's go ahead
and test this out in our network tool to
see if we are properly handling the
location.
Success. I hope your first challenges
went well for you. If you struggled a
little bit, that's okay. We are going to
get a lot of practice. But that's it for
this lesson. In our next lesson, we're
going to go ahead and handle getting a
single profile. I'll see you there.
In this lesson, we're going to go ahead
and create a route to handle getting a
single profile. So, we are going to need
to grab the ID from the pram. So, let's
go ahead and import that decorator.
And then we are going to call get and
we're going to need to grab the ID.
And let's go ahead and just call this
function find one. And so, we're going
to have a pram with an ID. And then our
ID is just going to be a string. And
just to make sure that we are properly
wh already made a mistake. This is going
to be singular. Just to make sure that
we are properly receiving the ID, we're
going to pass it through and just return
the ID in an object just like we were
returning a profile object. Now let's go
ahead and save it. And then we want to
test it out using our network tool.
And it does look like we are getting a
200 back. This looks promising. and
we're seeing the ID. Perfect. So, our
route is successfully receiving the ID
pram and passing it back to the client.
Now, we want to build up muscle memory.
So, let's go ahead and give you your
challenge. Let me go ahead and clear
this out and let me copy and paste in
your challenge. So, for your challenge,
I simply want you to replicate this.
You're just going to build out a route
to be able to handle getting a single
profile. You are going to look for an ID
prim and then you're just going to go
ahead and return that back to a client
in an object. Don't forget to use the
network tool to test out your code. All
right, good luck.
I hope that went well. So, let's go
ahead and go over the solution. So,
again, we're going to import param
because we want to grab the ID. So our
get is going to receive an ID and then
we'll call this fine one.
We're going to have a pram with an ID
and again that ID is going to be a
string and then we're just going to go
ahead and return an object with that ID.
As always, we want to test out our code.
So let's open up the network tab. Let's
go ahead and pass in a two this time.
Success. Looks like we're getting a two
back. And that's it for getting a single
profile. In the next lesson, we are
going to create a post route to be able
to create a profile. I'll see you there.
It's time to create a route to handle
post requests for creating a profile.
So, let's go ahead and import post up
here. Just start creating it down here.
And so, we are going to use the post
deck creator and we're just going to
call this function create. Now, before
we pull data out of the body, we'll tell
Nest what the data should look like by
creating a data transfer object. Think
of a DTO as a little shape contract for
each request. It lists the properties we
expect. For example, for our profile,
we'll have a name, which is going to be
a string, and a description, which is
going to be a string. We write it as a
class, not just an interface, because
classes stick around at runtime. that
lets Nest validation features pipes read
the class metadata and reject bad
payloads. So let's actually get started
with that. We'll go ahead and create a
DTO file. Typically you will see a DTO
file and a DTO folder. In that DTO
folder, we'll go ahead and create a new
file. We'll call this create profile
DTO. So this is going to be a TypeScript
file where we're just creating a class
and that class is going to have a name
which is a string and a description
which is also a string. Now we need to
hook it up in our controller. So let's
go ahead and import that. Now we want to
grab the body. So we're going to go
ahead and grab the body decorator as
well. So we'll call body here. And we
can just call this create profile DTO.
So we can just return the body here
directly. But I'm going to be a little
bit more explicit to just show that
we're creating a new object which is
going to represent our profile and then
we'll break that down. So let's go ahead
and return an object and then we're
going to have name. We're going to get
that name from the body. And same with
description.
Now at the time of this recording, the
network tool is still being flushed out
in Scribba. So, we can use it for get
requests, but for post, put, and delete
requests, we're going to need to use
curl requests. Now, I actually created a
bash script, which will make this very
easy for you. So, what we have here is
just a script that sends a curl request,
and that's essentially making a request
that's going to hit our API. Now, if
you're comfortable with curl, you'll
notice that I have the -x post, which I
don't think you need in newer versions.
I think it can interpret that this is
going to be a post request based off of
the body that we're sending, but I just
included it to be explicit. And in that
post request, we're sending a body with
a name and a description. Now, you can
change this as you see fit. Now, let me
show you how to test it out. So, we want
to go into our terminal,
and all we're going to do is type bash
and then the name of the file, host.sh.
Now you can see that we're getting a
2011 created and everything looks good,
right? 2011 means created, but this can
be very misleading. So one thing I
notice is we actually should be
receiving the response back and that
should be displayed in the terminal. So
I notice that the content length is
zero. This indicates to me that
something went wrong. Now maybe I
created this bug on purpose or maybe it
was an accident. You'll never know. But
one of the first things that I want to
check out is the runner. Ooh, it looks
like we are not properly importing our
DTO. So, let's go ahead and fix that.
So, you'll notice that I actually put
the file in the DTO folder. So, let's
actually scroll up and we're going to
add the folder. Let's go ahead and try
this again. And now we are successfully
getting the body back. We see a name and
a description. So, we're getting our
profile. Now, usually when you create a
resource, you'll usually see an ID as
well. We haven't actually generated that
yet, so we're not going to return it,
but we'll hook up the logic to create a
new profile soon. I think it's time for
your challenge. So, let me go ahead and
reset this. Let me go ahead and copy and
paste in your challenge. So, all I want
you to do is just replicate what we just
did. You are going to create our route
to be able to handle post requests. You
are going to create a DTO file and in
that DTO file you're going to have a
class with a name and description both
of which are going to be a string and
then you're going to hook that up in
your controller and then return the
body. Don't forget to run the bash
script at the end. Again, it's just bash
space and then the file name. All right,
go ahead and give this a try on your own
and then I'll see you on the other side.
I hope that went well. So, let's go
ahead and get started. Let's start with
creating a new folder. Call it DTO.
We're going to create a new file in that
folder. And we'll call it create profile
DTO. And export a class create profile
DTO.
And the name is going to be a string.
And the description is going to be a
string as well. So we'll need to import
this. So we know we're going to need
host and body. And then let's import
our DTO create profile DTO. And we are
going to import it from the correct
place this time. And I hope that you did
honestly create a bug, you got to
experiment with a runner because in
reality when you do get stumped, when
your code doesn't work and you have to
debug it, you often reinforce the
concept even more. But who knows, maybe
we'll create another bug. So we have our
post decorator and then we're going to
create our create function that'll take
a body and we're going to call this
create profile DTO and map that to the
DTO. All we're going to do is just
return a new object. That name is going
to get the name from the body and the
description from the body as well. So
let's test it out. And success. We are
seeing a 2011 and we are seeing name and
description. And that's it for our post
route. In the next lesson, we're going
to tackle the put route for updating a
profile. I'll see you there.
So, our put route is what we're going to
build out to update a profile. You might
have also heard of patch. Put updates
the entire resource while patch updates
part of the resource. We're not going to
go over patch because going over just
put helps us learn what we need to here.
I just wanted to mention this because
when I was starting out, I often confuse
these two. Something else to keep in
mind with put, it'll typically receive
an ID parameter in the URL and the
properties that it needs to update in
the body. Now, you already know
everything you need to in order to do
this on your own. So, let's go ahead and
jump into the assignment. I actually
created the DTO file for the update
profile for you. You'll just need to
create and export the class with the
matching properties. You can refer to
the create profile DTO as needed. In the
response of your controller, just return
an object with the ID, name, and
description you receive from the request
object. I also created the put shell
script for you. Notice that there is
just a random string here for the ID.
For now, you don't actually have to
change this to a working ID. We are just
focused on reading the request object
and returning the ID, name, and
description back to the client. All
right, I'll let you get to it. Good
luck.
I hope that went well. Let's go ahead
and get started with building out the
DTO class. We're going to export a class
called update profile DTO. And then
that'll have a name, which is a string,
and a description, which is a string.
Let's go back over to the controller.
Now, we're going to need to import put.
It looks like we have pram and body
imported. So, we're going to be able to
get the ID and the body. So, yep, we
just need put. Let's come on down here.
So, put is going to take an ID.
And then we'll just call this function
update. Update is going to take a pram,
which is going to be the ID. And that ID
is going to be a string. And then we're
also going to want to grab the body. And
we'll just call the body update profile
DTO.
And so we do need to import this.
And then we're just going to return a
new object.
And it's going to have the ID. And you
know what? We're just going to spread
the body in. That should do it. Let's go
ahead and test it out.
So we are just going to write bash
put.sh.
And success. We are getting an object
with the ID, name, and description. And
that's it for the put route. In the next
lesson, we'll go over delete. I'll see
you there.
Delete routes typically take an ID as a
parameter and return a 204 status code
on successful deletion. Up until now,
Nest has conveniently taken care of
sending the correct status code back to
the client. Unfortunately, it won't be
as simple with the delete request. If we
just return in the delete controller,
Nest will default to a 200. So in
situations like this where we want to
control the status code that we're
returning, Nest provides a convenient
way to do that. I'll go ahead and set up
the delete decorator for you so that I
can show you how this works. So we're
going to need to import three
decorators.
Delete HTTP code and HTTP status. Now
let's come on down here. So we are going
to expect an ID parameter and then for
now no matter what we are going to use
HTTP code to send a status more
specifically we're going to go ahead and
send an okay status which is just a 200
and we can just call this function
remove.
So we're going to have an ID pram
and then that is going to be a string.
We're not going to use that just yet,
but we're actually going to use it later
in the course. Now, this should send
back a 200. We don't necessarily need
HTTP status to set the status to be 200
because without it, it'll default to
200, but I'm including it because we'll
need to send a status code of 204. Let's
go ahead and do a curl request to test
this out. So, you'll notice we do have a
shell script here. This ID can be any ID
for now, but let's go ahead and test
this out, and we should get back a 200.
Success. It's working. Now, for our
purpose, this doesn't really accomplish
our goal. Remember, we want to send back
a status code of 204. That's your
assignment.
Looking up documentation is always a
healthy thing to practice. So, that's
what I want you to do. Go ahead and look
up what the HTTP 204 response is on MDN
and see if you can then figure out what
property on HTTP status represents a
status code of 204. Let me go ahead and
paste a challenge text in here for you.
So change it to the proper status code
and don't forget to test it. Good luck.
I hope that went well. So, what we're
looking for is no content. Let's go
ahead and test this out.
And there we go. We're getting back a
204.
Just a quick note, it's pretty common to
serve back a 204 regardless if the
profile being requested to be deleted is
found or not. When we go over exceptions
later in the course, I'll have you
practice serving up a 404 when the
profile isn't found with the delete
route. That's just meant to give you
more practice with handling exceptions.
But that pretty much covers most of the
decorators that you're going to use in
the controller for your first Nest app.
As your app grows, you'll likely use
more built-in decorators. And for that,
Nest docs will serve you well. We'll
come back to the controller layer later,
but for now, I think we've covered
enough of the basics. Let's move on to
the service layer.
Here's
a diagram of what a simple Nest app
might look like. So we have a root
application and then we have different
features. We have the O feature, profile
feature, and chat feature. Right now
we're building out the profile feature.
And in our profile feature, we have a
module file, a controller file, and a
service file. So our profile module
handles a lot of the imports for a clean
dependency injection. In our controller
file, we set up all of our routes.
Controllers are meant to handle HTTP
requests and they delegate more complex
things to providers. We're primarily
going to be going over one of the most
common providers you'll be working with,
services. The service layer is where
you're going to put a lot of your
business logic. So, in our app, our
controller handles the requests and our
service handles data storage and
retrieval. The service layer can
certainly do more than that, but that's
what we're going to use it for with our
profile feature. So let's go ahead and
set up our first service. We actually
used an CLI to generate the service.
All right, let's see what was created.
So it looks like we have a new spec file
and service file. We're not going to be
doing anything with the spec file, which
is just going to house a lot of our
automated tests. But let's take a look
at the service file. Notice the
injectable decorator above the class.
This enables our service class when
imported and used elsewhere to create a
new instance of it or reuse an already
created one. So you don't have to create
a new instance of it manually. Nest
handles this for you. Now the goal of
this course is to just teach Nest
concepts, not use an OM or an object
relational mapper for interacting with a
database. So while normally you'd store
this information in your database, we're
going to store our data in our service
class for now. Let me go ahead and copy
and paste that in. And now let me go
ahead and import something to be able to
create random IDs for us.
The random UYU ID method is just used to
create a unique ID and is part of Node's
built-in crypto module. It's not 100%
guaranteed to be unique, but if you got
it to generate two of the same IDs, you
are one of the luckiest people in the
world. It's pretty unique. Now, let's go
ahead and create the function that's
going to get and return all of our
profiles.
Let's call this find all. And then this
is just going to return our profiles
array. Now let's go ahead and hook this
up in our controller and finally return
a list of profiles.
So first let's go ahead and import our
service. Now we're going to add it to
the controller class through the
constructor.
So right now we're just returning an
empty array. Let's go ahead and actually
return the list of our profiles.
And as always, we want to test this out.
So far so good. We're getting a 200. And
we see our profiles. We have Brianna,
Jasper, and Leo. At last, we get to
build out a working profiles feature. In
the next lesson, let's handle getting
just a single profile.
All right, it's time to get your hands
dirty. Using what you just learned in
the last lesson, I want you to create
the service method for getting a single
profile and have the proper route in the
controller return the result of that
method. Remember, we're generating
unique IDs every time we spin this app
up. So, you'll need to get the current
list of profiles in order to get an ID
that exists. You can use the network tab
to be able to do that. And you just want
to hit this route right here to get all
of your profiles. Once you have that ID,
you can use the network tool to then
make a get request with the ID as a
parameter. So, here is our slug to get
all the profiles. Grab an ID from this.
And then we're going to get a single
profile and this is going to be used to
test our newly created service method
and make sure that we hooked it up in
the controller successfully. Also, don't
worry about handling the case where
there isn't a matching profile with the
ID given to us. We're going to go over
how to handle that in upcoming lessons.
For now, assume we're going to be given
an ID that does exist. So, just test
with that. And for your convenience, I
went ahead and just pasted the challenge
steps. Just make sure that you complete
them. You can check back if you forget,
but you know everything that you need to
in order to solve this challenge. So,
I'll let you get to it and I'll see you
on the other side.
I hope that went well. Let's go ahead
and jump into our service file. So, we
already have the method to be able to
get all of the profiles, but we're going
to have to think through how we're going
to execute with JavaScript just a little
bit more thoroughly. It's going to be a
little bit different, but if you're
comfortable with your fundamentals with
JavaScript, it should have been no
problem at all. Let's go ahead and call
this fine one. Fine one is going to
going to take a ID, which is going to be
a string. And then we want to just
return a single profile. So let's go
ahead and use the find method to do
that. And we are going to get a profile.
Let me just move this.
And whoops.
We want to match the profile ID of our
current iteration with the ID that we
are given here. And once that matches,
we'll go ahead and just return that
result from our find. And that should
give us what we want. So let's go ahead
and save this and then go on over to our
controller. Right now we are just
returning the ID that we get from the
pram. So we're going to have to change
that. Now we already imported our
service. So we can go ahead and just
type this profile service find one. And
don't forget to pass in the ID and that
should give us what we want. So in order
to test this, you could have gotten a
unique ID before you started writing
this. That's fine. But we mainly need it
for when we're going to be working with
trying to get a single profile. So I'm
just going to click send to give us our
new profiles. Uh let's go ahead and grab
Jasper. So we're going to grab this ID.
We're going to copy and paste it just
like this. And then we are going to just
enter that into the URL just like that.
So we are looking for specific profile
and that should give us back the entire
object, the entire profile. There we go.
There's Jasper. That's all there is to
it. Now you're going to get some more
practice with building service methods
and even just refreshing some of your
JavaScript fundamentals if you're a
little bit rusty. All right, I'll see
you in the next lesson.
All right, it's time to create a profile
and actually create a profile, not just
return the body that we're sending. So,
we're going to hook up the functionality
in our service layer. And I'll kind of
just go over some of the steps. You can
actually see them right here. They are
pretty long. Don't let this intimidate
you. The code is actually very minimal,
and I'll show you that as well. But I
just wanted to be very clear about this
and give you what you need to be able to
tackle this challenge. I'm very
confident that you're going to be able
to do it. So, let's go over some of
this. Uh, so essentially, you are going
to be creating a function in the service
file. We'll actually open that. We have
it right here. So, you're going to
create a new function. Uh, you could
just call it create or whatever you
want. And it'll take the body of the
post request as a parameter, which will
be the body that we're getting in the
controller. It needs to create a new
profile and add it to the profiles
array. Remember, each profile has an ID,
a name, and a description. And also,
it's good to remember that the backend
is where you'll typically create IDs for
new resources, not the client. You'll
notice that in the original array, we're
using random UU ID to do that. So, you
can utilize that as well. We'll also
want to return the new profile we've
created to the controller and have that
return it as a response in the client.
So, right now, we're just returning the
body. We're actually going to need to
call the new method that we create in
the service file and then return the
result of that. Now, once you've hooked
that up successfully, don't forget that
in the terminal, we can just call, let's
see, where is it? We can just call the
post sh file and that will essentially
hit our create route and that's going to
make a curl request to our post route.
Now, you don't have to change anything,
but if you want, you can change the name
and description to play around with it.
and you'll see your profile reflect
whatever you choose to add for the name
and description. I like to customize
things like this. I think it kind of
breaks me away from the monotonous flow
of just going through lesson after
lesson after lesson and it gets me to
critically think on my own. So change
some things, break some things,
experiment. I think that's always
healthy. But I would keep the changes
minimal at first until you actually
solve the challenge and then you could
play around with it afterwards. So when
you call the bash script uh you will get
a response with a 2011 and it will have
the same response body as when we tried
to retrieve a single profile. So it's
going to have the same structure. And so
again that structure is just going to be
an object with the ID, name, and
description. After you get the response
from the post request, go ahead and just
double check that it exists by making a
get request of the profile. Now that you
have the ID, we use the network tab to
do that. And if you want to see if your
profile is added, you can actually just
delete this and make a new request here
to actually see it added to our array.
Or you can just type in the ID as well
to get a single profile because in our
curl request, we're going to get a
response that actually gives us the ID
of our newly created profile. It's up to
you how you want to double check. Now
you know everything that you need to in
order to get started. Let's go ahead and
go back to the controller file. And
again, you have these steps and a couple
things to test that it is working
successfully. And don't worry, we're
going to go over this challenge
together, the solution after you tackle
the challenge on your own. So have fun
with it. All right, I'll let you get to
it and I'll see you on the other side.
I hope you had fun. All right, let's go
ahead and jump into the service file.
So, we're going to need to create a new
function. Before we do that, let's go
ahead and import the type from our
create profile DTO. Now, let's scroll
down and we are going to create our
create function. So, that I'm just going
to call what we're receiving and be
consistent with it. Create profile DTO.
And this is why we imported the type. So
now let's go ahead and just create an
object that's going to represent our
newly created profile and that is going
to have an ID. We're going to use random
UYU ID to be able to create that. And
then we are just going to spread the
rest of the body which is going to
contain the name and the description in
our new object. And then we have our
created profile but now we need to add
it to the array. So, we are just going
to push it and then we'll go ahead and
return the create a profile because we
want to go ahead and return that as a
response to let the user know that this
was the profile that was created. Now,
let's save it.
And in our controller,
we essentially want to I'm actually
going to just clear this text out
because it's quite a bit and a bit
noisy.
And all we're going to do, notice how
it's nice and clean because we separated
our logic into the service. We're just
going to return this profile service and
we're going to call our new created
function. And we are just going to pass
in the body that we received. And that's
it. Like I said, the code is pretty
minimal, but as you kind of jump from
different layers and you're separating
different concerns in a larger
application, it just takes some getting
used to and hopping back and forth. And
maybe this was fine for you. But if you
did feel a little bit overwhelmed with
all the steps, that's okay. We're going
to continue to practice. You're going to
get more comfortable with it. But, you
know, we could just be wrong. Maybe I
broke it. So, we still need to test
this. So, let's open up uh our tabs and
we are going to go to the terminal and
we're just going to type in bashhost.sh.
All right, success. Well, hopefully,
let's just double check. I like to
double check. Let's go to our network
tab and then we are just going to make a
new request to get all profiles. We see
Briana, Jasper, Leo. Uh-oh. So, it looks
like this is not working. This is why we
double check. Now, you guys might have
spotted the bugs and you might have just
been maybe yelling at your screen, dod
go back, change this, and good. If you
did, uh, if not, that's okay. Uh, but
this is why we double check. So, we're
going to go back to the service file.
Here's our two bugs. And I'm going to
tell you what kind of hinted towards me
being able to figure this out.
We have our runner. Don't forget to
check this. So in the runner, it looks
like we are just trying to get the DTO
type from a file that doesn't exist
because we made this plural when it
should be singular. We're creating one
profile. Now let's look at our profile
and we have a new bug. ID is declared
here. So let's go ahead and scroll down.
Now what we're doing is we are pushing
an object essentially that just has a
name and description. So if we go to
create profile, this is essentially the
type that this array is expecting and we
are just sending the wrong thing. We're
sending the body. We don't want to do
that. We want to send the created
profile. So let's go ahead and send the
proper object. Let's click save. Cool.
Seems like it's happy.
Now, I don't think it successfully sent
this and added the entry. Well,
obviously it didn't. And if I would have
noticed this and I would have taken a
closer look, you notice that there is no
ID, right? So, this could have been a
hint, but we have a lot of tools at our
disposal to be able to debug this stuff.
But, we need to go ahead and call the
bash script one more time. So, we're
going to type bash and then post sh. We
do see the ID. That looks promising. All
right, fingers crossed. Let's click
send. And ooh, looks like we might have
a bonus profile. So, we have Briana,
Jasper, Leo, and Kai. Success. Now, I
actually think it's pretty cool that I
created some bugs, honestly. Like, I can
still use refreshers. Everyone can still
use refreshers. And it just gets further
reinforced when you do hit that wall and
then you overcome it. So, if you are
creating bugs and you are struggling,
that is a good thing. that's where the
learning is happening. So, don't shy
away from that. But also, it was just
kind of cool to be able to go over how
we might spot some of these bugs. And
again, just a good reminder to use this
runner. It'll catch a lot of stuff for
you, double check if things aren't going
right. But that's it. We've created our
logic to be able to handle actually
creating a profile and returning it back
to the client. In the next lesson, we
will work on updating a profile that's
already been created. I'll see you
there.
All right. So, we don't want to stay
with the same profile forever. We want
the ability to update our dating
profile, and that's what we're going to
build out. So, let's go ahead and jump
into it. Here is your challenge. What
you're going to do is you are going to
add an update method in the service
layer. It's going to take an ID and an
object. In that object, you can expect a
name and a description. Essentially,
that object is just going to be what we
get from the body when we get a put
request. It should find the matching
profile based on the ID. It should
update that profile in the profiles
array. It should return the updated
profile. And then we're going to call
that function in our put controller
method and return the result. Now, we've
already gotten some practice with
hopping back and forth between the
service layer and the controller layer.
So, I trim the instructions a bit.
Hopefully, this is easier to read. Oh,
and one more thing. You'll probably
experience TypeScript errors when trying
to update a profile when there's no
match. So, for now, when there isn't a
match, just return an empty object.
Soon, we'll dive into exception filters,
which will help us better respond to
exceptions like when a resource doesn't
exist. You can use the bash script
already created for you here. If we open
this up, you'll need to replace this ID
with one that exists in a profile. So to
get that, you'll need to get all of the
current profiles with their unique IDs
and use one of those. You already know
how to do that. You've done that in the
last lesson. Or if you want to get more
experience with just making requests and
getting the IDs from those requests, now
that we've properly hooked up the post
route, you can create a profile of your
own and then just update it. All right,
I'll let you get to it. Good luck.
I hope that went well. All right, let's
go ahead and start off with building our
service method.
So, we are going to create a method.
We'll just call it update. Again, that
method is going to take an ID, which is
going to be a string. And then
we'll want to get the body. And we do
need to import this. So, I'll go ahead
and just quickly import the type. Let's
scroll on down and finish this.
Perfect.
So, we'll need to find the matching
profile and we can use the find method
to do that. So, let's go ahead and just
store this
and
whoops. Find is going to take uh let's
actually bring this down. Uh we'll
actually be explicit here. So, existing
profile
and we want to match the ID of our
current iteration
with the ID that we're passing through
here. And just so that we don't hit any
errors with trying to update the match
chain profile, which we're going to do,
if it doesn't exist, we're going to have
problems with that. So, let's go ahead
and escape early and just return that
empty object if we don't find a matching
profile.
And so we're just going to return an
empty object here. Now, we want to
update the name of the matching profile.
And then we're going to go ahead and
update the description as well. And then
the last thing we need to do is just
return that profile. Let's go back over
to our controller. And so right now
we're just returning the ID we received
from the prams and the body. So we can
go ahead and delete that. In fact, I'm
going to delete all of this.
And all we need to do is just return the
new created method that we're going to
call. We're going to return the result
from that. But we need to pass in the ID
and the body. That should do it. But as
always, we need to test. So let's bring
up the terminal. Let's go over here. So
we're just going to type bash and then
putsh.
Now, I just want to type this in because
this is not going to work because of
what I explained before. We're going to
have to change the ID. So, we're getting
an empty object cuz nothing is matching.
So, the very first thing we actually
need to do is we need to get all of the
profiles and we need to get an active
ID. So, let's grab Jaspers
and we're going to go ahead and go down
to let's actually just close that. put
we need to change this ID here.
Let's go ahead and change it. Let's
click save. Let's open up our terminal
again.
Clear this. And one more time. And
success. So, we were able to update the
profile. Again, we need a matching ID,
otherwise we just get an empty object.
And now, let's go ahead and just double
check. Let's go to the network tab.
We're going to make another request. And
we can see that Jasper was replaced with
Kai. Success. That's all there is to it.
Now, we are almost done with our main
service methods. We have one more method
to create, and that's our method to
handle removing a profile. We'll go
ahead and tackle that in the next
lesson. I'll see you there.
All right, let's go ahead and create our
last service method that's going to
match up with the routes that we
created. So, we are going to remove a
profile now. So, I'm going to go ahead
and give you your assignment. You're
going to create a method in the service
file to handle the delete request. It
should take an ID and delete the profile
that matches that ID. If there's no
match, don't do anything with the
profiles array. You just don't delete
anything. Regardless of whether or not
it finds a match, don't worry about
returning anything in the service
method. In a later lesson, we'll handle
the case where there's no match. So you
could just essentially return undefined
or not return anything at all because
undefined is going to be default. Our
controller is already properly
responding with a 204 and an empty body.
So you just need to call the service
method in the controller. That's it.
Don't forget to test your new route. We
have a shell script here. You're going
to need to open this up and change this
ID with an active ID. You already know
how to get active profiles, so you'll
need to do that. and then run the shell
script in the terminal. All right, I'll
let you get to it. Good luck.
I hope that went well. Let's go ahead
and build this out. So, let's go ahead
and just create a remove function here.
Um, we're going to receive an ID. That
ID is going to be a string.
Be a little bit explicit with
TypeScript. And then we are going to
need to get the matching profile index.
And what I'd like to use is splice to be
able to do this. So get the index. We're
just going to use find index. And we
want to match the profile ID of the
current iteration with the ID that we're
passing through. And then let's go ahead
and just splice the array if we find a
matching index. So if we don't find a
matching index,
we're going to get negative 1.
But anything above negative 1, we're
going to assume that we do find a match.
And then we'll just use splice
to edit our array in place. So, that
should be it for the service method.
Let's go ahead and go on over to the
controller.
And then we're going to remove this
text.
And all we're going to do, again, really
simple, call our newly created method.
And we need to pass in the ID. So, it
should work. But as always, we want to
double check. We want to test.
So, let's go ahead and just get some
active IDs. We're going to delete Leo.
Let's copy and paste this. Uh, we need
to go into our shell script.
And then we could just paste that there.
And then we're going to just go to our
terminal.
Let's go ahead and try it out. And I
think I said shell script. Um, bash
script is just a type of shell script.
So you can use those interchangeably in
this example. So we're going to just
type bash and delete.sh.
So we are getting a 204. Success.
Remember, we are serving up a 204
always. So, that could be a little bit
misleading. So, we're going to go ahead
and just make sure that the method was
called and it did work. Let's go back
over to our network tab and do another
scan. Looks like we only have Briana and
Jasper. So, that deletion was
successful. And that's it. We pretty
much created all the service methods to
match up with the logic that we need to
happen whenever we get a certain type of
request in our controller. So, this
might even be a good chance to take a
break if you've been coding for a long
time. Come back refreshed and I'll see
you in the next lesson.
Up until this point, we've mainly just
been building for the happy path in real
apps with the real users. This is just
unrealistic. We're going to also have to
handle edge cases and errors that pop
up. Nest actually comes with a built-in
exception layer which aims to handle all
unhandled exceptions or errors across
the application. If an exception is
unrecognized, Nest aims to at least
respond with a 500. Often though, we'll
want to control how we respond to the
client. So, let's jump into it. First of
all, we're going to need HTTP status and
HTTP
exception.
Let's go on over to our get with a
parameter of ID. So, if we're trying to
get a single profile, we want a profile
that matches that ID. But what if the ID
doesn't match? We want to be able to
handle that case. Well, for now, let's
actually comment this out and let's just
throw an HTTP exception and let the user
know that we didn't find the resource.
So, we're not even going to do anything
with the ID. We're just going to test
this new exception thing out. So, let's
go ahead and throw new HTTP exception.
And so, the message we're going to
deliver is a not found,
but an important thing that all the
clients are going to especially want is
the status code. And so, again, Nest
provides us with a lot of the common
status codes. And we're going to go
ahead and just serve up a 404.
So, in order to test this, we're going
to go ahead and try to get a single
profile and see if this works. If it
does, we're going to get a 404 in
response. So, let's test this out. And
let's just do some random ID that
probably doesn't exist. Not found. So,
we see a status code of 404. Let me
actually
scroll.
We're seeing the message not found and
we're seeing the status code of 404. So,
it's working. Nest actually provides a
set of standard exceptions that are
inherited from the base HTTP exception.
And often we'll throw that in the
controller. So, we'll just kind of clean
this up a little bit. Let's go ahead and
get rid of HTTP exception.
And we'll come back down. So, this isn't
going to work anymore, but what we are
going to use is not found exception.
So, that's essentially going to do the
same thing. Um, all I really care about
is serving up that status code. And this
will go ahead and deliver that. So,
let's go ahead and save with that. And
it'll respond to our client request no
matter what ID we give it. Not found.
And it has its own default message.
Notice we did not have to put that in.
So, this is a little bit cleaner. Now,
let me show you a really cool thing
about Nest. Let's go over to our Let's
actually comment this out. And then
we're going to go over to our service
file
and let's look at the find one. Let's go
ahead and just throw an exception before
the return. So no matter what, whenever
we call this function, we're always
going to be throwing an exception. But
we do need to import the not found
exception from nest common. Let's save
that.
And then we're just going to call that
here.
So let's go ahead and save this. And
then we're going to go back to our
controller and we are going to just call
profile service
and return it. In fact, we don't even
need to return it. I'm going to show you
this. So let's go ahead and save this
and we'll make the same request. And we
got a 404 again. Now we're not even
returning anything, right? So the cool
part is
we just call this function and any
errors are thrown here, they're going to
bubble up to the controller and nest
just provides that convenience for you.
Right? So this is a pretty convenient
because as you'll see in a second, this
will be really useful for this method.
Right? What happens when we don't find a
profile? So again, we go back to the
controller. We don't even need to return
this. We can. It doesn't matter if we
return it or not because once we throw
this exception, this takes over and this
is what's served back to the client. And
what does a client see? Status code of
404 not found. So let's actually be
practical about this. We don't always
want to throw this. What we probably
want to do is check if there's a
matching profile. If there is a matching
profile, we want to go ahead and return
this. If not, then we want to go ahead
and return that 404 or throw an
exception and allow that to be caught
and served up to the client. So, let's
go ahead and delete this.
And we are going to store this in a
variable. Let's call it matching
profile.
If there is no matching profile,
we want to go ahead and throw that new
not found exception. And we can actually
provide a custom error message. I just
wanted to show you this. Um, let's make
it a practical profile with ID
ID
not found.
And then if this condition is never met,
we want to go ahead and just return the
matching profile. Let's go back over to
our controller. So we are calling this.
We can actually get rid of this just to
clean it up. So we are calling this
method and if we find an ID, it should
return a profile that actually matches.
And if not, we should get that 404. So
let's test it out.
All right. So we do get the error
message by default. But if we want a
custom message to also send to the
client, we have profile with ID and then
the ID that we passed through not found
with a 404. So obviously this ID doesn't
exist. Let's go ahead and just take a
look at all profiles.
Let's grab Briana's
and then we're going to go ahead and
make a request to Briana.
And so this is just demonstrating our
conditional logic is working. If we do
match a profile, then we serve up the
profile that's matching. If not, we get
that 404 error. I think this bubbling up
behavior is really convenient for
beginners because in this method, we
already know that if we don't have a
matching profile, let's just go ahead
and handle that exception here, throw
it, and we're done. No matter what,
we're calling the function in our
controller and letting the method in our
service file just handle everything
because it has some of the context of
what it needs to in order to either
return a matching profile or not. Feel
free to play around with this as you
like, but in the next lesson, I'm
actually going to give you several
challenges to be able to practice this.
So, I hope that made sense. If it
didn't, you'll get practice in the next
lesson. I'll see you there.
In this lesson, I'm going to go ahead
and give you a couple challenges. you
are going to update the update and
delete methods to be able to throw the
proper exception when a matching profile
is not found. You'll have to change each
method a little bit differently to make
that work. But remember, if there is a
matching profile, we still want to
return that matching profile. So, make
sure that works. All right, I'll let you
get to it. Good luck.
I hope that went well. Let's go ahead
and tackle the update method. So we
already have the conditional to check if
there isn't a matching profile. So we
just need to change line 61. And we are
going to throw our not found exception
here. And then let's go ahead and
provide that custom message as well. And
we'll include oops we'll include the ID.
And that should be it. Let's go on over
to our remove method. So, we are
only editing the array in place if there
is a matching index. So, we're going to
change this slightly. Let's bring this
down. This a little bit of space. And
then our conditional is something we're
going to have to change as well. So, I'd
like to opt out of the method and throw
that exception early if there's no
matching profile index. So let's go
ahead and throw our not found exception
here. And again let's provide the custom
error message. I'm going to cheat. Copy
and paste this.
All right.
So that should do it. Now we are
throwing the exception if there's no
matching profile index and we are
editing the array in place if there is a
matching profile. Now, this will work
because
we have our decorator to automatically
serve up a no content, which is going to
be a 204 status code. But if we do throw
that exception, this is what's going to
take priority. But as always, we want to
test this. So, let's go ahead and open
this up. And then we're going to go
ahead and get all of our profiles.
So, here's how I'm going to test this.
There are different ways that you could
have gone about it. I'm going to go
ahead and edit Briana and then try to
delete her. So, let's go ahead and
change these IDs. Oops.
And delete as well.
Now, let's test this out in the
terminal. So, with Briana, let's go
ahead and see if we can update her
profile. So, we're just going to call
our shell script. And we did get a
result back. Hopefully this is working.
I like to just do a quick sanity check.
Let's go ahead and click send. So we
have the same ID with Kai and a new
description. So that was successful. Now
let's see if we can delete Kai.
And we got a 204. So let's just make
sure that Kai was actually deleted. And
it looks like he was perfect. So now we
know that that profile no longer exists.
So it still works when we have a
matching profile. Let's see if it works
when we don't have a matching profile.
Let's go ahead and go back over to the
terminal. Let's clear this and then
we're going to try to edit. And it looks
like we are properly getting a 404.
And let's try the delete.
And we are getting a 404 with the delete
as well. Success. So, I purposefully
showed you a non-conventional way to do
this so you could see the power of Nest
bubbling up those errors to the
controller. Honestly, for basic apps, I
think it's fine to throw HTTP specific
exceptions inside the service and let
them bubble up. But as an application
grows, it's cleaner to let the
controller decide which HTTP exception
to return. This keeps services focused
on business logic and makes them
reusable in non-HTTP contexts where an
HTTP exception just wouldn't make sense.
In the next lesson, I'm going to show
you a more conventional way to do this.
Now, again, if you're just starting out
and for basic apps, I think it's
completely fine to handle HTTP
exceptions in the service layer, but let
me go ahead and show you a little bit
more of a conventional way to do this.
Now let's shift the responsibility of
handling HTTP exceptions to the
controller. So we'll go ahead and just
do this for getting a single profile. So
right now we're throwing the exception
here. What I'm actually going to do is
just throw an error. Let's go ahead and
save that. Let's go on over to our
controller. So we're going to go ahead
and wrap this in a try catch block. And
then we are going to just catch the
error. And in here we're just going to
throw the not found exception
and we're going to get the error message
and pass that through. So let's go ahead
and test this out.
Open up the network tab and then we're
going to go ahead and just we're going
to pass a random ID that is not going to
exist and we're getting a not found.
Now, on your screen, you might see a
TypeScript error. I'm not worried about
fixing this because we're going to move
on and do something a little bit more
specific. You might be thinking that
this only handles a very specific case
and that it's not handling other types
of common errors that we would handle.
And you'd be right. In Nest, your
service layer often handles requests to
the database. and your OM or whatever
library you use to structure your
queries often will have built-in error
objects that you can throw or return in
your service function and let your
controller figure out a matching HTTP
exception. In actual applications, we
would probably want to catch the error
in the controller like so. So maybe
something like
if error is instance of database
exception,
then we're going to go ahead and throw
new not found exception
here. Now, this isn't going to work
because we haven't hooked up any
database or imported any types for that,
but I just wanted to show you something
that you might commonly see in a
controller. And for many apps, the base
exception filter can handle a lot of
cases for you. But if you ever want more
control, you may want to build your own
exception filter. And for that, the
nests are a great resource for whenever
you want to dig a bit deeper. But once
more, I just want to stress I'm kind of
just showing you a little bit more of a
conventional way to start handling some
of the exceptions. Again, in your basic
app, I think it's completely fine to
throw an HTTP exception in the service
layer. And I honestly would just start
with that. Keep things simple for you
just so you can get an application and
API up and running because Nest has a
lot of depth to it. And I want you to be
very careful about how deep you dive
just to get a basic application up. But
that's pretty much all I want to go over
with exceptions. Now in the next lesson,
we're going to go over pipes and talk
about transformation and validation.
I'll see you there.
Pipes and nest have two typical use
cases, transformation and validation.
Transformation allows us to transform
input data to the desired form, such as
from a string to an integer. Validation
ensures the input data meets certain
rules before it proceeds further in the
request life cycle. Now, we're going to
go over both, but this lesson is
dedicated to transformation. Since our
ids are UYU IDs, why not transform
those? Let's use the parse UYU ID pipe
to try and transform our ID which we get
as a string into a UYU ID. So let's
start with our imports. We are going to
need
pars uyu ID type and then let's actually
go ahead and import
uh we'll make this a type.
So we're going to import the UYU ID type
from crypto.
If we move on down to our get a single
profile route, we have our ID pram, but
it remains a string. So let's go ahead
and transform it into a proper UYU ID.
And then for TypeScript, we already
imported the type.
Now, as always, let's test this out. So
we're going to need the network tool. We
first need a list of active ids to test
this out. So let's go ahead and grab
those. And if we take a look at the
response, we can go ahead and grab
Briana's.
And let's just make sure this is still
working. Perfect. We see Brianna's
profile. Now, UYU IDs have a very
specific format you got to follow. So,
let's actually just try deleting the
last character.
And what do you know? We see validation
failed. So, it attempted to transform
it, but it detected a bad UU ID format.
So, it was unable to do so. And we got a
validation error. This is exactly what
we want because now our route can always
expect a proper UYU ID to work with. All
right, it's time for your challenge. Let
me go ahead and copy and paste in the
challenge text for you.
So, if you remember, we have an ID pram
for both the put and delete routes. I
want you to go ahead and use the parse
UYU ID pipe on those as well and
transform that ID. And as always, don't
forget to test your code. Remember, you
have to put and delete shell scripts to
do so. All right, good luck.
I hope that went well. Let's go ahead
and implement it with a put first. So,
we have the ID pram. We want to go ahead
and parse this. And then we also want to
change this for TypeScript.
And I'm actually going to go ahead and
just copy and paste the same thing for
our delete route.
As always, we want to test this out.
Let's grab an active profile. So, first
we'll try to change the profile, Brianna
Watts, and then we're going to try to
delete it.
Let's head on over to our put and then
we're going to replace this ID and we're
first going to try to change it.
All right, let's just double check that
it actually did change.
And we see Kai. Perfect. Now, let's go
ahead and test it out with an improper
UU ID.
It looks like our pipe is working and
failed to transform it because we did
not have a proper UYU ID for our string.
Let's just make sure Kai is still there.
All right. Now, let's try to delete Kai.
But before we do, let's give it an
improper UU ID.
And it looks like our pipe is working.
Let's give it a proper one.
And I went ahead and just pasted Kaizen
just to make sure that we can actually
delete this successfully.
All right, so we are getting a 204.
Let's test it out. Profile not found.
Success. That's all you need for a first
look at built-in pipes. You've seen how
they can transform raw strings into UYU
IDs, and there are plenty of others you
can try out. Now that our route
parameters are guaranteed to be the
right type, we need to be sure each
request body also contains valid values.
In the next lesson, we'll use Nest
validation pipe, add class validator
decorators to our DTOS, and watch Nest
reject bad payloads before they ever
even reach our controller.
While Nest provides some simple, common
out-of-the-box pipes for us to use, we
may want to get more granular with what
we expect from the data. For example,
maybe we want each name to have a
minimum amount of characters. So, let's
go ahead and add that. Before we start
though, we'll need to install two
libraries that'll give us a bunch of
extra decorators that we can use to
validate incoming data.
That's class validator and class
transformer. While we'll only be
importing from class validator in our
simple validation examples, it's common
and even recommended in the nest docs to
install both. Class transformer lets
validation pipe convert plain JavaScript
objects into instances of classes so
decorators can read them. They both work
really well together, especially as your
transformations and validations get more
complex. Now that these are installed,
we can add a few useful decorators to
the create profile DTO class. Let's go
ahead and head on there.
So, first let's go ahead and import
them. So let's just check for a string
and then we're going to give a specific
length that the name needs to have. So
it's really simple to add these
decorators.
So length is going to take a minimum
amount of characters and a maximum. So I
think three is good for the minimum and
then we'll say 100 for the maximum. That
should do it. And then we just want to
make sure that the description is a
string as well. Now, this won't quite
work yet. We first need to bind the
validation pipe. Let's bind the pipe
instance to the route handler body so
that our pipe is called to validate the
body. So, we'll do that in our
controller.
So, let's go ahead and bind it like so.
And then we are going to need to import
it.
Now, let's go ahead and test it out.
So, we're actually going to go to our
post shell script and then let's try to
create kai and just make it ka and see
if we get rejected.
And we are getting a bad request and the
message name must be longer than or
equal to three characters. Now, let's go
ahead and add the i back and try it
again.
And success. Now it's time for your
challenge.
Let me go ahead and copy and paste in
the challenge text.
So you're going to add the validation
pipe for the body in our put route.
Using class validator, add a couple of
decorators to our update profile DTO to
create more granular restrictions for
the values. And feel free to look up
class validator and just explore what
decorators it provides. Maybe try
something different than the length
decorator that we used. All right, I'll
let you get to it. Good luck.
I hope that went well. So, let's go
ahead and get started in our update
profile DTO. Let's import our
decorators. And you know what? Let's go
with min length. So, name is going to be
is string and length or min length.
We'll set that
to let's just stick with three. and then
our description is going to be a string.
Let's head on over to our controller.
And then again in the body, we're going
to create a new validation pipe and
let's test it out.
So it looks like we got validation
failed. Let's see what happened.
So if we look back at our terminal,
hopefully you remember what to do with
this. So we first need to make sure that
we are providing a proper UYU ID. So
let's go ahead and grab one. We'll just
copy and paste this.
Now I expect this to be successful
and it was. Now let's break it.
name must be longer than or equal to
three characters. It's working. Also,
notice how we bound each validation pipe
to each body. While this gives us more
granular control over which route we
want to apply it to, it's more common to
protect all of your endpoints by binding
it at the application level. Let me go
ahead and show you how to do that. So,
first we're going to get rid of the two
additions here.
And then we're going to go into our
Bootstrap file, which should be main.
And then we're going to set up a global
pipe.
And that is going to be our validation
So, we're going to need to import that.
Let's going back over to our controller.
So, we don't have it here or here. Let's
test it out. If we look at our putshell
script, this should break.
name must be longer than or equal to
three characters. Perfect. It's working.
By the way, when I say break, I just
mean the payloads rejected. But you get
the gist. Now, given that Nest is full
of classes, class validator is a
fantastic library to give you a ton of
extra convenient validations for your
data.
Guards and Nest have one purpose to
determine whether a given request will
be handled by the route handler or not.
For example, think authorization. Maybe
we just want admins to be the only one
who can delete profiles or we want users
to only be able to update their own
profile. We can actually use the CLI to
get us started. So, let's go ahead and
open up the terminal. And then we're
going to go ahead and generate a new
guard for profiles. All right, let's
take a look. So in profiles, we do see
that there is a new guard. Remember, a
guard's single responsibility is to
determine whether or not a given request
will be handled or not. So the main
thing it needs to do is return a true or
false based on the logic you set up.
Let's go ahead and bind this to a route
to get it working.
So we can actually get rid of validation
pipe and we're going to import use
guards from nest common. And then let's
go ahead and import our guard and we
need to bind it. Let's go ahead and bind
it to the delete route.
So we take a look at our guard. It looks
like we are returning true. So it should
let the request pass through. And then
if we take a look at delete, what we
probably should get is a validation
error because this is not a proper UYU
ID.
So let's test it out.
All right. So we got our validation
error. Now let's see what happens when
we return false.
And we get a 403 forbidden. Perfect.
That's exactly what we want at a
fundamental level. That's how a guard
works. It either returns true or false,
accepting or rejecting the request. Now,
let's take a closer look at this custom
guard. Now, I don't expect you to
remember all this. I just want to show
you this. If you use something like
passport.js, it provides the decorators
to be able to just import the proper
guard in your controller and bind it
without you having to go into creating
some custom guard for yourself, unless
you want to. But I just want to show you
this to give you a little bit more
context. So every guard must implement a
can activate function. We can get
information from the request through
context. And we need to decide if we
should allow this request to pass to our
controller method or not. So for
example, let's go ahead and grab the
request.
And now let's pretend that we have an
authenticate function.
So I'm not going to import it. I'm not
going to create it, but let's just
pretend we do. And then in that
authenticate function, we want to pass a
request and let our authenticate
function deal with the authentication
logic. And we applied a guard to a
specific controller method. But as you
may suspect, just like validation pipe,
guards can be applied to a broader scope
such as the controller class or globally
as well. Guards are very commonly used
for authorization. I wanted to avoid
diving deep into authorization in this
course and just focus on the
fundamentals of Nest, but the concept of
guards is pretty simple and Nest's great
documentation for implementing them.
Most likely though, you're probably just
going to use the passport integration if
you want to implement authorization in
your app. That's it for our lesson on an
intro to guards. I'll see you in the
next lesson.
Congratulations on completing this
course. You just built a REST API with
Nest building blocks, modules,
controllers, services, and DTO's, plus
pipes for transformation and validation,
guards for authorization, and exception
filters for graceful error handling.
That's miles beyond the typical Hello
Express app. Give yourself a pat on the
back. You've shown that you're curious
and are taking your growth into becoming
a better back-end developer seriously.
So, I bet you're asking, what's next? If
you want to continue learning and diving
deeper into Nest, consider connecting a
database. Try the type OM or Prisma
guides in the docs to persist profiles
instead of using an in-memory array. I
actually switched from Prisma to type OM
recently and I'm loving it. You can also
set up authentication and authorization.
Follow the official Passport recipe.
Passport's a really common thing to use
with NestJS and set up some role-based
guards with it. And you can also use
encryption and hashing utilities for
passwords. And if you want to write some
automated tests for what we built even
so far, go for it. Nest shifts readyto
use unit and end to end test
scaffolding. Fire up justest and protect
your controllers and services. Or if you
have more experience with frontend and
you finally want to build out your own
API documentation that you've been
utilizing when working with other
backend teams, add swagger or open API
to your project and generate live API
docs for your project. Nest makes this
really easy. My own projects, I love
using Nest CLI plugin that autogenerates
the open API docs from decorators or
deploy your application. Read about Nest
recommended deployment practices to get
your website live so that you can show
others what you built. Now, in my
personal opinion, if you're pretty fresh
with a backend, that is going to be a
pretty big hurdle. If you want an easier
hosting solution, I highly recommend
third party guides for something like
hosting your Nest app on Render,
Railway, or Heroku. It really simplifies
the DevOps part of hosting your web app.
But if you're going to start anywhere,
start with the Nest Docs. If you truly
want to get better with Nest and you
want to build great things with it,
you're going to be spending a lot of
your time there. Now, you can continue
learning Nest and continue building on
the project we built together, but maybe
start with building out your own basic
API first. Try to replicate what we just
did, but with your idea, or even take
one of your Express apps and convert
that over to Nest. Just whatever you do,
don't get trapped in tutorial hell. If
you want this stuff to stick, if you
want to grow as a software engineer, you
have to build. And remember, Nest is
built for large maintainable TypeScript
apps. So, if it still feels a little
overwhelming, that's normal. Give
yourself weeks or even months of
building with Nest, and those decorators
will feel like second nature. And most
importantly, thanks for coding along
with me. Software engineering is a
never- ending journey, and that's one
thing I love about it. There's always
room to grow and more challenges to
tackle. If you'd like to follow along on
my journey and where I also share a ton
of advice for junior developers, check
out my YouTube channel. And you're also
welcome to follow me on X or LinkedIn.
But that's it for this course. Go build
something awesome and happy coding.